Guide to the Livingston Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- - - - 3 Mary Eleanor Curran (1883–1969) m. 1916 Henry Hopkins LIVINGSTON (1887–1960)
Airplanes -- Piloting -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Boats and boating; Camping -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works -- 1903; Cattle trade -- Wyoming; Land speculation -- New York (State); Military camps; Mine buildings -- Pictorial works; Mining corporations -- New York (State) -- Records and correspondence; Political campaigns -- New York (State) -- New York; Real estate investment -- New York (State); Regattas; Ships -- Pictorial works; Ships -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 20th Century; Shipping; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Campaigns -- Puerto Rico; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Pictorial works; Sheet music; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Military bases; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States -- Posters; World War, 1939-1945 -- Aerial operations; World War, 1939-1945 -- Correspondence; Acoma (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Hudson River Valley (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Description and travel; Hudson River Valley (N.Y. and N.J.) -- History; Hudson River Valley (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Pictorial works; Hudson River Valley (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Social life and customs; Account books; Albums; Albumen prints; Ambrotypes (photographs); Audiovisual materials; Autograph albums; Badges; Business records; Cabinet photographs; Visiting cards; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Diaries -- United States -- 20th Century; Diplomas -- United States -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States; Drawings (visual works) -- Italy -- 18th century; Engravings (prints) -- France -- 19th century; Exercise books; Fans (costume accessories); Financial records; Gelatin silver prints; Gem photographs; Guidebooks -- West (U.S.); Intaglio prints; Invoices -- United States -- 19th century; Invoices -- United States -- 20th Century; Legal files -- United States -- 19th century; Letterpress copybooks; Lithographs -- France -- 19th century; Medallions (medals); Military maps -- France -- 20th Century; Photograph albums -- United States -- 19th century; Photograph albums -- United States -- 20th Century; Portrait photographs; Scrapbooks; Sheet music; Snapshots; Sound recordings; Tintypes (prints); Training manuals; Viewbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Woodcuts (prints) -- Japan -- 19th century; Promotional materials; Bigelow, Poultney, 1855-1954; Curran, Eliza Phillips Mulford, 1852-1936; Curran, Henry H. (Henry Hastings), 1877-; Curran, Henry Hastings, 1841-1864; Curran, John Elliott, 1848-1890; Debucourt, Philibert-Louis, 1755-1832; Duncan, Francis King, 1878-1970; Gatine, Georges Jacques, 1773-1831; Gillies, Robert C.; Lanté, Louis Marie, 1789-; Lasteyrie, C. de (Charles), 1759-1849; Lecomte, Hippolyte, 1781-1857; Levick, Edwin, 1869-1929; Lewis, Henry, 1819-1904; Liepshutz, Elaine B., 1920-2001; Livingston, Alida Schuyler, 1656-1727; Livingston, Anna P. (Anna Pendleton), 1866-1967; Livingston, Archibald R. (Archibald Rogers), 1868-1952; Livingston, Edmund P. (Edmund Pendleton), 1857-1888; Livingston, Edmund P. (Edmund Pendleton), 1889-1972; Livingston, Emeline Cornell Hopkins, 1859-1940; Livingston family; Livingston, Henry H. (Henry Hopkins), 1887-1960; Livingston, Henry H. (Henry Hopkins), 1918-2008; Livingston, Herman, 1856-1936; Livingston, Herman, 1883-1951; Livingston, Herman T. (Herman Tong), 1827-1899; Livingston, John, 1750-1822; Livingston, Mary Eleanor Curran, 1844-1969; Livingston, Robert, 1654-1728; Livingston, Susan Bard Rogers, 1835-1911; Maggiotto, Francesco; Miller, Walter V., 1903-1980; Mulford, James Hervey, 1802-1885; Raymond, Rossiter W. (Rossiter Worthington), 1840-1918; Rhinelander, Philip Mercer, 1869-1939; Rosenfeld, Morris, 1884-1968; Shaler, Nathaniel Southgate, 1841-1906; Sheafer, P. W. (Peter Wenrick), 1819-; Simpson, Clyde Vincent, 1898-1947; Stebbins, N. L. (Nathaniel Livermore), 1847-1922; Tiepolo, Giovanni Domenico, 1726?-1804; Vernet, Carle, 1758-1836; Watrous, Harry Willson, 1857-1940; Willard, Stephen H.; Columbia University. School of Mines. Class of 1891; Michele Mang & Co; New York Genesee Company of Adventurers; Oak Hill Iron Mining Company; Paramount Oil Company; Pennsylvania. National Guard. Infantry Regiment, 13th -- Pictorial works; St. Paul's School (Concord, N.H.) -- Students; United States. Army. Cavalry Regiment, 12th. Troop H; United States. Army -- History -- Pictorial works -- Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916; United States. Shipping Board; United War Work Campaign, Inc; Yale University -- Rowing; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1870; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1898; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1909; Art Treasures Exhibition ( 1857 Manchester, England)
- Early Papers, 1772-1883; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: John Livingston Papers, Herman and Sarah Hallet Livingston Papers, and Livingston Family Legal Records.
  Biographical/Historical note
  John Livingston (1750–1822)
  John Livingston was born in New York City, one of the twelve children of Robert Livingston Jr. (1708-1790), the third and last Lord of Livingston Manor, and his wife Maria Thong Livingston (1711-1765). An aide-de-camp to General (and New York State governor) George Clinton during the Revolutionary War, John Livingston was engaged in land speculation in the Hudson River Valley and upstate New York. He built his home, Oak Hill, along the Hudson in the northwest corner of Livingston Manor, around 1794. Oak Hill was one of three large houses Livingston built during the 1790s; one was nearby and the other across the Hudson in his planned community of "Esperanza." With his first wife Mary Ann Le Roy he had ten children; his second wife was Catherine Livingston Ridley, a first cousin whom he married in 1796.
  Herman Livingston (1793–1872)
  John and Maria Livingston's youngest child, Herman, was born at Oak Hill, attended Union College, and had a career as a merchant with a shipping line based in Hudson, New York. In 1821 he married Sarah Lawrence Hallet (1795-1868) of Long Island. The couple had three children, John Henry (1822-1846), Cornelia (1824-1851, married Clermont Livingston), and Herman Tong Livingston (see Series II).
  Scope and Contents
  Description of the Papers
  Series I consists of papers of the earliest members of the family to reside at Oak Hill, John Livingston and his son Herman, accompanied by a group of the Livingston family's land and legal records. John Livingston's papers comprise one folder of miscellaneous correspondence and financial documents to or referring to him; the latter includes a letter from Elkanah Watson. Additional material concerns Livingston's involvement in the New York Genesee Company of Adventurers, and the building of the Reformed Church of Linlithgo, New York. The former documents the activities of Caleb Benton, Oliver Phelps, Peter Ryckman, and the Indians Joseph Brant and The Infant, among others, along the Pre-Emption Line in the area of Canadesaga (now Geneva), New York, area; included is a 1796 survey map of Towns 6 & 7 in the Phelps & Gorham purchase along Crooked (now Keuka) Lake.
  Herman Livingston's papers include correspondence, financial, and legal papers, as well as a diary he kept from 1869 until the day before he died. Also in his papers is a folder of material related to the family's involvement in the Catskill Ferry and one regarding their land holdings on the west side of the Hudson River: in the1790s, the family invested in Esperanza, a settlement meant to develop as a rival to Hudson, the village on the east bank of the river, just north of Oak Hill; in 1800 Esperanza acquired its present name of Athens.
  The third subseries, Livingston Family Legal Records, contains manuscript documents and printed forms, including deeds and quit-claim deeds, leases, mortgages, indentures, articles of agreement, and powers of attorney related to transactions occurring across New York State, though primarily in Columbia, Albany, Greene, and Otsego counties, and in Pennsylvania; also included is a blank indenture form printed by Childs and Swaine (circa 1791) for Robert R. Livingston of Clermont. The documents are filed in chronological order followed by folders of maps and surveys. One deed in Box 123, folder 1096, concerns the Susquehanna Company (1795), and is among several in the subseries that are written on vellum.
  - John Livingston papers
    - Account/day book, 1792-1823
      General note
      Contains accounts for Livingston Manor and Oak Hill, certain sloops, and some diary entries
    - Correspondence and financial papers, 1787-1823 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Portraits [photographs and prints of portrait painting], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Will, 1810
    - New York Genesee Company of Adventurers, 1787-1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reformed Church of Linlithgo, 1814-1816 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Herman and Sarah Hallet Livingston papers
    - Correspondence, 1829-1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diary and account book, 1869-1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Financial papers, 1822-1868 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ledger/day book, 1823-1834
    - Legal papers, 1815-1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper clipping, re: Oak Hill slaves, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Cited in Marion Harland's Some Colonial Homesteads and Their Stories (1897)
    - Portraits [photographs and prints of portrait painting], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Athens property, 1810-1883 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Catskill Ferry, 1839-1846 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Henry Oothout estate, 1810-1817 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - John Livingston estate, 1822-1843 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Livingston family legal records
    Arranged by type of document, thereunder filed chronologically by date of creation
    - Deeds, leases, mortgages, indentures, etc., 1778-1810 (Box 2, Folder 15-19)
      Includes photostats from other collections
    - Deeds, leases, mortgages, indentures, etc., 1811-1862 (Box 3, Folder 20-25)
    - Maps and surveys, 1772-1853 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Includes printout (from microfilm) of deduction of title to Oakhill Farm
- Herman T. and Susan Rogers Livingston Papers, 1856-1910; Series II; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Correspondence, and Personal Papers and Photographs.
  Herman T. Livingston (1827–1899)
  Herman Tong (sometimes spelled Thong) Livingston was born June 12, 1827, at Oak Hill, the son of Herman (1793-1872) and Sarah Lawrence Hallet Livingston. Educated at Poughkeepsie, New York, he studied law in New York City, but did not practice. Livingston entered the shipping trade while in his twenties, first with his own clipper ship Architect, and in 1852 with his steamship, Black Warrior. He later formed Livingston, Crocheron & Company, and ran a fleet of cargo vessels to Cuba and the southern states. His ships were impressed into military service during the Civil War; afterward he became a partner in the shipping firm of Livingston, Fox and Company. Parallel investments in New York City real estate enabled him to retire from the shipping trade in 1873. Livingston had summer homes in Newport, Rhode Island, and Southampton, New York, and he died at the latter place on October 20, 1899. He was buried in the family vault at Linlithgo, Columbia County, New York, where a carved memorial tablet records his middle name as Tong, as do the family record pages in his Bible held in this series.
  Susan Rogers Livingston (1835–1911)
  Susan Bard Rogers was the daughter of Archibald Rogers (1793-1850) and Anna Pierce Pendleton Rogers (1796-1883) of Hyde Park, New York. She was born at 7 State Street, the New York City home of her grandfather, merchant Moses Rogers, and married Herman Livingston on December 6, 1853. Susan Livingston served as an officer of the National Society of the Colonial Dames of America, and in her last years resided at 20 Washington Square North, in New York City.
  The Livingstons had six children: Herman (1856-1936), Edmund Pendleton (1857-1888), John Callendar (1862-1956), Anna Pendleton (1866-1967), Archibald Rogers (1868-1952), and Sarah (1871-1959). Further information on Herman, Anna, and Archibald can be found in Series III, IV, and V respectively, and on John in Series XII. Edmund P. Livingston attended St. John's School in Sing-Sing (Ossining), New York, graduated from Yale College in 1879, and worked as a banker in New York before entering the cattle business in Wyoming (1882) in partnership with a cousin, Archibald Rogers (1852-1928) of Hyde Park, New York. Livingston remained in the West until he became ill with consumption; he was brought back to Oak Hill by his brother Herman and died there on December 10, 1888. Sarah (Sallie) Livingston was born on August 22, 1871, married George Herbert Williams (1860-1937), a physician; they lived in the Hudson Valley and in the Philadelphia suburbs. She died in Ardmore, Pennsylvania, on June 19, 1959.
  Herman and Susan Livingston were friends with the noted landscape painter Frederic Edwin Church (1826-1900) and his wife Isabel, who began building Olana, their grand Persian-style home, on a promontory a mile north of Oak Hill in 1860. The series holds copy images of the Churches, a photograph of an oil portrait of Isabel (Box 4, folder 34) at the Olana State Historic Site, and a daguerreotype by Jeremiah Gurney of a portrait drawing of Frederic (Box 159, folder 1266); the original drawing is unlocated. In addition, Box 4, folder 32 contains a photocopy of an 1883 letter to Herman Livingston from Frederic Church. Two great-grandchildren of these long-time friends, Henry Hopkins Livingston and Maria May Burroughs, were married in 1942 (see Series VIII).
  Herman and Susan Livingston's Correspondence files primarily contain letters from their children. Most notable are those from their son Edmund, which range from childhood notes to letters from his European travels (1878), to nearly twenty written while he was exploring cattle ranching in the West (1882-1888). There is, however, no correspondence concerning Herman Livingston's business ventures.
  The bulk of the subseries Personal Papers and Photographs comprises financial records from the last years of Susan Rogers Livingston: invoices and receipts from her homes in New York City (where she lived from November through May) and Cornwall-on-Hudson, New York. Invoices exist for goods and services purchased, as well as for household repairs, improvements, and utilities; they show that she frequented the New York's major retailers John Wanamaker, B. Altman & Company, Tiffany, and Arnold, Constable & Company, and supported a variety of charities including the Children's Aid Society, the Five Points Mission, and the Charity Organization Society of New York. Fragments of her wedding dress are filed in the papers of her daughter Anna (Series IV, Box 34, folder 290).
  - Correspondence
    - Livingston, Anna P. (1866-1967) [daughter], 1900 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1857-1888) [son], 1868-1896 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Includes condolence notes from Edmund's colleagues, and Yale College obituary record
    - Livingston, Herman (1856-1936) [son], 1868 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Rogers, Anna Pierce Pendleton, 1856, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Contains two letters written by her and one to her
    - Miscellaneous, 1877-1906 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Personal papers and photographs
    - Architect and Black Warrior[Livingston merchant ships]: photographs of prints, 1899, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Illuminated Bible (New York: Harper & Brothers), with manuscript family record (1856-1967) between Old and New testaments; copies of record in Box 4, folder 38, 1846
    - Church, Frederic Edwin: daguerreotype by Jeremiah Gurney of a portrait drawing of Frederic Edwin Church, likely by Samuel Worcester Rowse (1822-1901), circa 1856
    - Church, Isabel M. Carnes: photograph of an oil portrait [at Olana], circa 1910 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Iselin, Fannie, and mother, circa 1870 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Livingston children [formerly in album], circa 1865-1870 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1857-1888) [son]
      - Photographs, circa 1876-1880 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Photographs with horse and carriage at Oak Hill, circa 1880
      - Scrapbook of clippings on Yale College athletics, 1876-1877
    - Livingston family history notes, 1896-1907, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
      Includes photocopies of H.T. Livingston's brief autobiography
    - Livingston, Herman T.
      - Daily journal, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Miscellaneous papers, including indenture and letters patent, 1877-1887 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Newspaper pages with shipping advertisement, 1853 Mar 13
      - Photographs, circa 1860-1890 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - State of New York Supreme Court case publications, 1850 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Livingston, Susan Bard Rogers
      - Colonial Dames of the State of New York, 1897-1907 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Daughters of the Cincinnati, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Financial documents
        - Bank records, 1907-1908 (Box 5, Folder 45-50)
        - Bank records, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 51-52)
        - Invoices and receipts, 1906-1907 (Box 6, Folder 53-56)
        - Invoices and receipts, 1908-1910 (Box 7, Folder 57-61)
      - Photographs, circa 1865-1891, undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Rogers, Archibald and Anne Coleman
      - Gift book: Angel Over the Right Shoulder, 1856 (Box 7, Folder 63)
      - Portrait photographs, circa 1880, 1896, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Rogers, Moses and Sarah Woolsey, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, formerly in album, circa 1865-1875 (Box 7, Folder 66)
      Includes portraits of unidentified reverend of Christ Church, Hudson, New York, the family dog "Bruno," Charles Carpenter of Livingston Fox & Co., Henry Hopkins, several unidentified portraits (cartes de visite and cabinet cards), commercial cartes de visite from Scotland and Ireland (circa 1865) and a piece of mechanical equipment (1865)
- Herman and Emeline Hopkins Livingston Papers, 1820-1958; Series III; 7.7; (18 boxes)
  Series III is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Personal Papers, Photographs and Prints, and Cornell/Hopkins/Howland Family Papers.
  Herman Livingston (1856–1936)
  Herman Livingston was born in New York City, June 24, 1856, the eldest of the six children of Herman T. Livingston (1827-1899) and Susan Rogers Livingston (1835-1911). He was educated privately and entered Yale College with the class of 1878, where he rowed with the varsity crew and was tapped for the Skull and Bones senior society. He did not graduate, but the university awarded him his B.A. and an honorary master's degree in 1899. Livingston spent the majority of his life at Oak Hill, and inherited the estate upon his mother's death. He farmed the property, served as a director of the Hudson River Trust Company, and over his lifetime owned ocean- and river-going yachts including his schooner the Amorilla, which he sailed on the Hudson River. Livingston was the proprietor of the Oak Hill Iron Mining Company (see Series IX); both he and his wife Emeline invested in the Lewis F. Payn Oil Company's works in West Virginia. He was also an investor in the Paramount Oil Company (see Series X). Herman Livingston died at Oak Hill on December 30, 1936, and was buried in the family vault in nearby Linlithgo, New York.
  Emeline Cornell Hopkins Livingston (1859–1940)
  Emeline Cornell Hopkins was born on November 26, 1859, in Catskill, New York, a village directly across the Hudson River from Oak Hill. She attended Miss Haines and Mademoiselle de Janon's English and French School for Young Ladies, a private school in New York, in the 1870s, and was married to Herman Livingston on November 9, 1882. The couple had three sons: Herman Jr. (1883-1951; see Series VI); Henry Hopkins (1887-1960; see Series VII); and Edmund Pendleton (1889-1972), a graduate of the Taft School and Yale University (1911). During World War I he served in the Aviation Corps of the United States Army, married Kathleen O'Connor, and became a banker in New York. Emeline Livingston died on April 4, 1940, and was buried in the Livingston family vault.
  Emeline Livingston's parents were the New York iron importer Henry Hopkins (1820-1873) and Mary Elizabeth Cornell Hopkins (1833-1887), the daughter of Samuel Mott Cornell (1806-1883) and his first wife Emeline Julia Howland Cornell (1816-1854) of New York. Hopkins was a descendant of the Mayflower passenger Stephen Hopkins. Emeline Howland Cornell was a native of New Bedford, Massachusetts. Emeline Hopkins Livingston's youngest brother, Charles Vernon Hopkins (1872-1933), was also a Yale graduate (1896) and spent his adult life in New York City and Catskill; he saw active service in Europe during World War I.
  Series III holds material covering the lives of Herman and Emeline Livingston, and Mrs. Livingston's ancestors. The subseries Correspondence holds both business and personal letters addressed to the couple, prominent among them letters written during World War I by their sons Henry (serving stateside) and Edmund (in France), Herman's brother Archibald (in France), and Emeline's brother Charles (in France and Germany). Also of note here are letters written by Herman's brother Edmund from Wyoming and other points in the American West while he was starting his cattle business. Other interesting items are letters from Livingston's Yale classmate Poultney Bigelow, which are illustrated by him, and from his Yale friend William Howard Taft (in the Invitations folder), and in the General Correspondence folder, a letter from and photograph of Lew Yuk Liu, the son of the Chinese ambassador who had visited the Livingstons in 1889. Five folders of letters, invoices, and statements (vessel reports) from Rogers & Webb document investments made by Herman Livingston in ten cargo schooners through the Boston firm of shipowners and brokers. The vessels carried cargo such as lumber, fertilizer, coal, flour, molasses, and salt between the United States and the Caribbean, Canada, South America, and Europe; the correspondence also reveals that Livingston was involved in providing timber for use in shipbuilding. The subseries ends with several folders of condolence notes, cards, and telegrams sent to Emeline Livingston upon the death of her husband.
  The Personal Papers subseries primarily holds serial narrative and financial documents: daily diaries kept by Herman Livingston between 1887 and his death in 1936, which were continued by his widow through her death four years later, with random bank and tax records kept by the couple.
  The Photographs and Prints subseries holds a few photographs of the Livingstons and their three boys, as well as non-military marine images that may or may not have been owned by Herman Livingston (some bear initials of his brothers EPL and ARL) but, due to his interest in and ownership of yachts and schooners, were filed here. Among the images of pleasure craft are those taken by noted marine photographers Edwin Levick, (1869-1929), Morris Rosenfeld (1884-1968) and N.L. Stebbins (1847-1922), and several examples of "Nautotypes" distributed by the sailing journal Rudder. Some of the images appear to have once been framed, and have retained their period mats and mounts.